Okay,
today's דף *daf* is בבא קמא ס *Bava Kamma Samech*, בבא קמא
*Bava Kamma* 60, and we pick up one line from the top
or the second line, שלח ביד פיקח *Shalach B'yad Pikeach*, and as
I'm recording this, I'm recording it from ירושלים עיר הקודש *Yerushalayim Ir
HaKodesh*, and our learning should be in the זכות *zechut* of the
protection of our חיילים *chayalim* and חיילות *chayalot* and of the safety
and security of our people. Okay, so the משנה mishna. *mishna* said
that if a person is making a fire
and it's presumably the fire was only big enough to and it
would have gone out by itself, it doesn't say that in the
משנה mishna *mishna* but that seems to be the case, and then
somebody comes and adds something to it and makes it a substantial
fire, then the latter person is liable. So if you had a
type of a small fire and somebody came and added wood, the
person who added wood, he's the one who makes it the fire.
If you had wood and obviously somebody lit the wood, then the
one who lit the wood is the one who makes it a
fire. And if you have somebody who comes and it's a small
fire and you have somebody who comes and blows on it and
turns it into a fire that's substantial and that is potentially dangerous,
then the one who came and blows on it is the one
who is liable. You could define this both in terms of like
negligence, but it really also seems here similar to discussions around the
בור bor. *bore* that it's a question of like whose fire is
it, and the person who made it into a potential danger, it's
that person's fire. That could also be connected to the question of
אשו משום חציו isho mishum chitzo, *eisho mishum chitzo* and אשו משום
ממונו isho mishum mamono, *eisho mishum mamono*. Okay, so now on the
part of the משנה mishna *mishna* where it says that if a
person blew on it that made it into a substantial fire, he's
the one that is liable, we have the following גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
שלח ביד פיקח *Shalach B'yad Pikeach*, that's actually part of the משנה
mishna, *mishna* we're skipping over. אמר רב Rav, נחמן בר יצחק מאן
דתני ליבה לא lo משתבש ומאן דתני ניבה לא משתבש *Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak: Man d'tani liba lo mishtabesh u-man d'tani niba lo
mishtabesh*. If you have the version ליבה *liba* to blow on it,
that's not a bad version, that's not an error version, a corrupt
version, and if you have the version ניבה *niba*, that's also not
a corrupt version. Both of those are legitimate versions of the language
of the משנה mishna, *mishna*. מאן דתני ליבה לא משתבש דכתיב בלבת
אש esh *Man d'tani liba lo mishtabesh, d'chtiv: belabbat esh*. ליבה *Liba*
comes from the word לבת אש *labbat esh*, the flame of the
fire, so ליבה *liba* would mean to turn it into a flame.
And that's so that's why that's a legitimate version. ומאן דתני ניבה
לא משתבש דכתיב בורא ניב שפתים *U-man d'tani niba lo
mishtabesh, d'chtiv: borei niv sefatayim*, God who creates the speech of the
lips, so it means like the blowing of the lips. Okay, both
of those are legitimate versions. ליבתה רוח כולם פטור pattur, *Libta ruach
kulem patur*. If however, one person added the wood and one the
fire or one blew on it and it was not substantial enough
to do anything and it would have gone out and then the
wind made it into a substantial fire, then they're all exempt because
none of them did anything. You know, of course, it raises a
question of like whose property is it in? If it was my
wood and my fire, am I really exempt if I'm aware of
it? If I'm aware of it, shouldn't I be responsible to put
it out? And if I don't put it out, then I do
become liable like similar to breaking a vessel in רשות הרבים *reshut
harabbim* and you're responsible to clean it up, if you're not, then
it's like your בור *bore*. Anyway, that's not exactly discussed. Let's assume
that we did our thing and we walked away and it was
in רשות הרבים *reshut harabbim* and it was in a public space
and then the wind came and blew it. Okay, and again, presumably
also was not a wind that we could have anticipated, that's a
question of רוח מצויה או o אינה מצויה *ruach metzuya o einah
metzuya*, which okay, so now let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. *Tannu rabbanan*: ליבה וליבתה רוח *liba v'libta
ruach*, so if let's say here's a ברייתא *braisa* that deals with
the case not in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, let's say it's you
plus the wind. You blew it and the wind blew on it
and אם יש בליבתה כדי ללבתה חייב chayav, ואם לאו פטור ptor,
*im yesh belibta k'dei le-labbta chayav v'im lav patur*. If your blowing
had enough to make it into a substantial fire on its own,
then it's your fire and you're liable, but if not, if your
blowing was nothing and it was only combined with the wind, then
you are off the hook because you are not the one who
turned it into a fire. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says wait
a minute, that's a little bit strange, assuming that they did it
like at the same time,
which it seems to be how the ברייתא *braisa* is different than
the משנה *mishna*. So if you know there's a wind blowing and
you're adding your blowing, so you're sort of combining with the forces
of nature and the ingredients present, aren't you the one controlling everything
and aren't you the one making it a fire? So even if
yours didn't have enough, if it contributed and why isn't this all
considered to be your actions? So that's what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says, but it asks that question by comparing it to שבת shabbos,
*Shabbos*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אמאי ליהוי כזורה
ורוח מסייעתו *Amay? Lehevei k'zoreh v'ruach mesayato*. Why? Why is this true?
Why shouldn't this be like a case like winnowing, not זרע *zera*,
not seeding, winnowing, which winnowing is when after the cow like after
you cut down the wheat and the cow walks over a board
plank with like spikes and it separates the husk from the kernel.
Now you have to separate now it's husk is broken off from
the kernel and now I have to separate the chaff from the
wheat. So the first way you do this is you take it
all and you throw it up in some type of a basket
and you throw it up and the wind comes and the wind
blows away the chaff which is lighter and the wheat falls down
and that's your first process in separating the chaff from the wheat.
That's called זורה *zoreh*. So when you do זורה *zoreh*, you're using
the wind to blow away the chaff and you're חייב chayav *chayav*,
that's actually the exact act of what זורה *zoreh* is. So why
not here too say it's you know you're using the the wind
and therefore it's your action? So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. אמר אביי Abaye הכא במאי עסקינן כגון ש... *Amar Abaye: Hecha
be-may askinan? K'gon she...* אמר אביי הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שליבה מצד
אחד וליבתה רוח מצד אחר. So אביי says what we're talking about
is you didn't actually do it together with the wind. You blew
on one side and the wind was blowing on the other side.
So like if you could imagine, if you were to split the
fire down in half, right? So your actions sort of went—did didn't
do anything. The wind on its own didn't combine with what you
did. What you did wasn't substantial enough by itself, and therefore the
wind is the thing that turned it into a flame. And what
you did was completely inconsequential to what the wind was. You weren't
sort of participating with the blowing of the wind. Alright, so that's
what he says.
And now the גמרא Gemara gives another answer. רבא Rava אמר—רבא says—כגון
שליבה ברוח מצויה וליבתה רוח שאינה מצויה. kegon she'liba b'ruach metzuya v'libsa
ruach she'eina metzuya. No,
you were using the wind, but even with the wind that was
present and normal winds that you could have expected, it was not
going to turn into a flame. And then came this big gust
of wind and turned it into a flame. So in that type
of a case, your actions were not—you can't manipulate something that you
can't anticipate. So you weren't using the ingredients at your disposal. You
did something that was insubstantial, and something else came completely unrelated to
and unconnected to your actions and turned it into a fire. Now,
again, it does raise an interesting question of, okay, I didn't turn
it into a fire, but again, if I was still there, because
this seems to be happening simultaneously, and it turned into a fire
and I'm the one that's been working with it, don't I have
a responsibility to like put it out? You know, assuming that it's
not uncontrollable from the get-go. So that is not discussed, but I
think that's obviously a question that's just ever present in all of
these סוגיות. sugyot. Okay, but anyway, it's not your fire in that
case. רבי זירא אמר Rabbi Zeira amar כגון דצמרא צימורי. kegon d'tzamra
tzimurei. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said it's a case where you
like—you were like barely blowing on it, you know? You were just,
like רש"י Rashi sort of says, like you know, like the type
of blowing you do on your hands to warm them up. So
therefore you're not using the wind. What you're doing is not like
half and half, and you're not—you know, the wind is doing its
own thing and you're doing something completely insubstantial.
Okay, so again, none of these are פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat
seems to be every case that you are not doing enough by
yourself, you're exempt. So finally we're going to have an answer that's
going to deal with—that's going to embrace that פשט. pshat. רב אשי
אמר, Rav Ashi amar, כי אמרינן זורה ורוח
מסייעתו—when ki amrinan zoreh v'ruach mesayato do we say that winnowing in
the wind helps you, you're liable? היינו לענין שבת. hainu l'inyan shabbos.
That's when it comes to שבת, shabbos דמלאכת מחשבת אסרה תורה. d'melechet
machshevet asra Torah. Because the תורה Torah says, you know, מלאכת מחשבת
melechet machshevet is learned from the משכן, mishkan, and it has to
be something intentional. Now this is very strange because normally מלאכת מחשבת
melechet machshevet is an exemption. If you tried to do one thing
and you did another thing, even slightly different, you tried to throw
it ארבע אמות arba amos and it went שמונה אמות, shmoneh amos,
you tried to pick the black date and you picked the white
date, because it's not precisely your intent, that's not a real חילול
שבת. chilul shabbos. Here we're using מלאכת מחשבת melechet machshevet to make
you liable. Here we're saying since it focuses on the intentionality and
therefore what you're trying to do is separate the wheat from the
chaff, and therefore we don't focus on the fact that your action
by itself couldn't have done it all on its own and that
you had to use the wind, because we allow ourselves to focus
on the end result as well, and you achieved the desired end
result. Okay. אבל הכא גרמא בעלמא הוא וגרמא בנזיקין פטור. aval hacha
grama b'alma hu v'grama b'nizikin patur. But here it's just גרמא, grama,
it's just indirect, and indirectness when it comes to actions are exempt.
Now again, besides the fact that מלאכת מחשבת melechet machshevet is normally
a limiting factor, not a way to expand your liability, it's very
strange that שבת shabbos here is more expansive in its definitions than
נזיקין. nezekin. Because any time you're dealing with a question of איסורין—did
issurin I do a
violation?—you want to focus on the fact of: did I do the
act? Not just: did I achieve my end result? But איסורין issurin
are always about the prohibited act. Whereas by נזק, nezek, the
aspect of negligence is a huge one. So clearly there's negligence here.
So why—and you're exempt. So if you say אשו משום חציו, esho
mishum chitzav, fine, you could understand that it has to be all
more of you. And maybe that's explaining why the גרמא grama gets
you off the hook even though you're using the wind that's present.
If you say אשו משום ממונו, this would be like a little
ironic. But again, maybe there you could say if it's not an
ownership of a fire, even though you're negligent and you were negligent
to let it escape and you were clearly negligent to create it,
since you didn't directly create it, we can't call it your fire.
It's not like you dug the בור. It's not like you totally
did it, so you don't own it, it's not your fire. But
again, it's quite strange that the liability for שבת Shabbos, is broader
than when we're dealing with an action focused rather than the liability
for... נזיקין Nezikin where we tend to be dealing with a negligence
focus. That's one point to make. The other I should say though,
is that by שבת, Shabbos, you know, what's being ignored here, and
maybe this is what רב אשי Rav Ashi means, but what's being
ignored here is the fact of a standard way of doing something.
Like let's talk about the איסור issur of, you know, the מלאכה
melacha of cooking on שבת, Shabbos, right? So on שבת, Shabbos what
do you do? You put something on the fire. Now, the moment
you put it on the fire, you haven't exactly cooked it. The
moment that you put it on the fire, it's just sitting there
and slowly, slowly warming up and it takes an hour to cook.
But when it actually finishes cooking, you're חייב, chayiv even though you
didn't cook it, you didn't transform it with your hands and so
on. You put it in a situation, but that's called cooking. The
same way that's what's called winnowing is you throw it up and
the wind comes, whereas here... so that's what I think you could
have said and maybe that is what רב אשי Rav Ashi means,
that's the classic way the act is done. Because we do normally
have a principle by שבת that גרמא gramma is פטור, you know?
And if I use the wind to help me with something that
normally it wouldn't be the normal way to do it, I don't
know, I threw something up intentionally to have the wind blow it
onto the stove and then it was on the stove and it
cooked. Am I חייב for that? It's מלאכת מחשבת, meleches machsheves, presumably
not. So it sounds like one way to understand רב אשי Rav
Ashi is that this is what cooking means, you know, what this
is what winnowing means, whereas here, in order to make it the
fire, you have to make it all by yourself. Still, it is
strange that you know that your actions are going to combine with
the wind and turn it into a fire and that you still
are somehow exempt. And תוספות Tosafos makes this point, if you look
at this little תוספות והכא גרמא בנזיקין, Tosafos v'hacha gramma b'Nezikin,
תוספות Tosafos says, מתוך כך נראה דאם שנים הביאו עצים או הליבו
שניהם ואין בכל אחד כדי להלבותו פטור דתימה הוא. Mitoch kach nireh
d'im shnayim hevi'u etzim o helivu shneihem v'ein b'chol echad k'dei l'halvoso
pattur d'teima hu.
תוספות Tosafos says, let's replace the wind with your friend. So you
know, you both contributed half, you know, you contributed half a flame
that wouldn't have been
enough, he contributed another flame that by itself would have gone off,
but the combination does it. You both blow. One blowing wouldn't have
been enough, but the two blowings are enough. Are we going to
say that combined you made a fire and that you're going to
be exempt? I mean, why should it be different if it's the
wind or your friend? But then תוספות Tosafos but that's bizarre. Two
people can make a fire that's actually dangerous and they're exempt because
no one did any one thing by himself? Presumably, it's a שותפות,
shutafus, it's a joint fire. Okay, so here, you know, would we
say... so it seems like that's the difference, that because it's an
issue of who made it and who owned it, if two people
made it equally, they're equal owners. But if I and the wind
made it, well the wind can't be an owner of the fire
and so it's not my שותף, shutaf, so okay, so I would
have said I used the wind, that's why it's all my fire.
And then we say no, it's not my fire at all. Very
bizarre conclusion. Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה. השולח
את הבערה ואכלה עצים או אבנים או עפר חייב. Hashole'ach es hab'eira
v'achla etzim o avanim o afar chayav. Somebody sent a flame out,
you know, and it went and it ate the wood or stones
or dirt, you know, it didn't consume them, but it blackened them,
you're obligated. שנאמר כי תצא אש ומצאה קוצים ונאכל גדיש, Shene'emar ki
seitzei eish u'matza kotzim v'ne'echal gadish, a fire goes out and it
finds thorns or thistles and it burns up
a haystack, a stack of grain, I should say, או הקמה, o
hakama, or standing grain, או השדה, o hasadeh, or the field. שלם
ישלם המבעיר את הבערה. Shalem yeshaleim hamav'ir es hab'eira. The one who
makes it shall definitely pay. Okay, so it's just saying presumably the
חידוש chidush of the משנה of eventually to translate a פסוק pasuk
into הלכה, halacha, presumably the חידוש chidush is to say that
even if it didn't consume something and destroy it, it just blackened
it with fire damage, that is enough. I should mention that the
השולח את הבערה, hashole'ach es hab'eira, and we had that in the
previous משנה as well, is an interesting verb to be using because
there's a פסוק pasuk right here that actually in משפטים Mishpatim that
says, right,
ושלח את בעירה. v'shillach es b'eiro. What the גמרא Gemara, explains to
mean שן ורגל. Shen v'Regel. But the... those who sort of explain
the פשט pshat of the תורה Torah say that actually that sounds
like you are sending forth your flame, you are intentionally
burning something, rather than the next פסוק pasuk which is כי תצא
אש, ki seitzei eish, it escaped, you know, as opposed to intentionally
lighting something fire. Could be the difference between אש משום חציו eish
mishum chitzav and אש משום ממונו, eish mishum mamono, and that the
difference in the פסוקים psukim is when it says ושלח את בעירה,
v'shillach es b'eiro, it says מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם, meitav sadehu
u'meitav karmo yeshaleim, you have to pay the best. It doesn't say
that when it's כי תצא אש. ki seitzei eish. So it's interesting
that the משנה, that's in the פשט, pshat, you know, and we'll
see something similar in the גמרא coming up about a difference between
when you light it in your property or you light it in
somebody else's property. But anyway, the משנה, it's interesting that it chooses
to use the verb המשלח, hamishalle'ach, השולח. hashole'ach. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, למה לי דכתב רחמנא
קוצים גדיש וקמה קמה ושדה? Lama li d'chsav rachmana kotzim gadish v'kama
kama v'sadeh? Why did the תורה Torah have to give all those
examples of different types of things that the fire is burning? צריכי,
Tzrichi, you need all of them.
If it had said just the thorns and the brambles, הוה אמינא,
hava amina, קוצים הוא דחייב רחמנא kotzim hu dechayiv Rachmana
משום דשכיח אש בהו. mishum deshachiach esh bahu. Okay, that's the type
of thing that it lights to, kindling or whatever this type of
stuff that the fire will easily take hold of; then that's why
you're חייב because then clearly you're negligent ולא
שכיח דפשע, v'lo shachiach d'pasha, and therefore it's likely that you were
negligent.
But, אבל גדיש, aval gadish, if it actually burned a stack of
wheat דלא שכיח אש ביה d'lo shachiach esh beh that the fire
is not
common—it's not common that it'll go all the way out and burn
a stack of wheat, a mound of wheat—ולא שכיח דפשע, v'lo shachiach
d'pasha, it's not likely that you would be negligent, אימא לא, eima
lo, I might think no. It has to tell you that even
if that's what happened,
you were going to be held responsible even if you said, "Oh,
who could have thought it was going to go all this distance
and get that
stack over there, that haystack or that wheat stack?" Okay. ואי כתב
רחמנא גדיש, v'ee kasav Rachmana gadish, if it had just said the
case of the stack of the mound of a grain, הוה אמינא
גדיש חייב רחמנא hava amina gadish chayiv Rachmana משום דהפסד מרובה, mishum
dehefsed merubeh, that's when the תורה Torah says you have to pay
because that's serious
loss.
ואי משום דהפסד מרובה הוא, v'ee mishum dehefsed merubeh hu, אבל קוצים
דהפסד מועט הוא, aval kotzim dehefsed muat hu, but thorns and
thistles or whatever kindling, דהפסד מועט הוא, dehefsed muat hu, that's only
a small loss to the owner, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you
wouldn't be obligated, which again is quite
strange because who cares if it's a dollar or who cares a
hundred dollars, if I'm liable I'm liable. But maybe this is just
saying the fire is something escapes and it's not you yourself who's
doing it, so maybe the תורה Torah would have limited it. Okay,
קמה למה לי? kama lama li? Why did the תורה Torah have
to say standing grain? מה קמה בגלוי אף כל בגלוי. ma kama
begalui af kol begalui. To tell you that the same way standing
grain is something that it's exposed, anything exposed; but this is the
פטור, the exemption of טמון באש, tamun baesh, something buried in the
haystack you're going to be
exempt for. ולרבי יהודה דמחייב אהיזקי טמון באש, ulRabbi Yehuda demechayiv ahizkei
tamun baesh, but what about רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that
things that are buried you are obligated for fire payment? So, קמה
למה לי? kama lama li? Why did it have to say standing
grain? לרבות כל בעלי קומה. lerabos kol baalei komah. To say everything
that is standing, it doesn't have to be stuff growing from the
ground; רש"י Rashi says even animals, any type of property. Okay, ורבנן
לרבות כל בעלי קומה מנלהו? veRabbanan lerabos kol baalei komah minalhu? And
where do the רבנן Rabbanan know to include that? נפקא להו מאו
השדה. nafka lehu meoh hasadeh.
It says "or the field", so the extra או o is coming
to include something else. רבי יהודה איידי דכתב רחמנא או הקמה, Rabbi
Yehuda aidei dechtav Rachmana o hakama, because it said the או o
by the standing grain, כתב או השדה, kasav o hasadeh, it says
the extra או o by the field, even though one או is
enough to tell
you we mean something in addition. Okay, so שדה למה לי? sadeh
lama li? And why did it say field? לאתויי לכנירו וסכסוכה אבניו.
latuyei lechniro vesichsicho avanav.
This is actually what seems like the חידוש chiddush of the משנה
is, to tell you even if it doesn't destroy something, even if
it just burned and charred your plowed field or your stones, that's
still fire damage and even though it didn't actually destroy. ולכתוב רחמנא
שדה ולא בעי
הני, velichtav Rachmana sadeh velo baei hanei, so just write field and
tell me if even fire damage then certainly if it destroys something.
צריכי, Tzerichi, you need all of them. אי כתב רחמנא שדה הוה
אמינא מה שבשדה אין מידי אחריני לא. ee kasav Rachmana sadeh hava
amina ma shebasadeh in midi achrini lo. If it had just said
field I would have thought that it meant only something that's actually
in the field and not other things. So which is meaning I
would have interpreted the word שדה sadeh differently, I would have interpreted
it not to mean the ground but I would have interpreted it
to mean the wheat and the haystack and all those things. But
after it said wheat and haystack and then it says שדה, sadeh,
clearly it means even the ground. Okay, אמר שמואל בר נחמני אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Shemuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yochanan, now we're going
to get into a whole agadic section. אין פורענות בא לעולם אלא
בזמן
שהרשעים בעולם. ein puraniyos ba lolam ela bizman shereshaim baolam. Bad things
only happen to the world when there are evil people in the
world. Now you might say often good people suffer. Okay, but we're
not done.
So he says ואינה מתחילה אלא מן הצדיקים תחילה. veina matchala ela
min hatzadikim techila.
But the people who actually first suffer when suffering comes to the
world are the righteous people. Not very fair. שנאמר כי תצא אש
ומצאה קוצים. shenemar ki tetze esh umatza kotzim. When a fire goes
out and finds the thorns. אימתי אש יוצאה? eimasai esh yotzei? When
does this fire come, this burning, this destructive force? בזמן שהקוצים מצויין
לה. bizman shehakotzim metzuyin la.
When there are thorns that are the very easy or like kindling,
stuff that's very easy for it to catch on. But thorns here
means the evil people. So evil
people whether unleash bad things in the world and ואינה מתחילה אלא
מן
הצדיקים תחילה. veina matchala ela min hatzadikim techila. Whether they unleash it
personally because they're doing it or whether they unleash it because in
some sense of the metaphysical way that God created the world or
God in sort of an intentional way is bringing it, but it
comes because of evil in the world and bad people, but then
the people who suffer first are the righteous. שנאמר ונאכל גדיש. shenemar
veneechal gadish.
Okay, and the גדיש, gadish, the pile of grain is consumed. ואכל
גדיש לא נאמר. vachal gadish lo neemar. It doesn't say that it
then after consuming the קוצים kotzim it then consumes the
גדיש, gadish, אלא ונאכל גדיש, ela veneechal gadish, and the גדיש gadish
was consumed. And this is again the Rabbis trying to deal with
the reality of צדיק ורע לו, tzadik vera lo, they didn't really
explain why it's fair, but they recognize that that's part of how
the world works. Okay. תני רב יוסף, Tani Rav Yosef, מאי דכתיב
ואתם לא תצאו איש מפתח ביתו עד בוקר? mai dikhtiv ve'atem lo
tetze'u ish mipetach beito ad boker? So since we were dealing with
a statement, you know, about like the צדיקים tzadikim and about unleashing
evil, we're going to have similar. What does it mean, you know,
when משה Moshe tells them about מכת בכורות, makat bekhorot, don't go
out of your household until morning? Because
why not? You know, God is going to protect them. No. כיון
שניתן רשות למשחית אינו מבחין בין צדיקים לרשעים. keivan shenitan reshut lammashchit
eino mavchin bein tzadikim leresha'im.
Once there's permission for destructive forces to be unleashed, you know, it
does not distinguish between good and evil, then, you know, innocent people
get caught up and innocent people suffer. So it's a little different
than saying it starts with the righteous people, but it recognizes the
same reality when there is destructive forces and, you know, happening in
the world, the righteous people suffer. ולא עוד אלא, Velo od ela,
and now we're going to go make the point we made before,
beyond this, אלא שמתחיל מן הצדיקים תחילה. ela shematchil min hatzadikim techila.
It actually does start from the righteous. שנאמר והכרתי ממך צדיק ורשע,
shene'emar vehikhrati mimmekha tzadik verasha, I will destroy from you צדיק tzadik
and a רשע rasha starting with the צדיק. tzadik. Okay. בכי רב
יוסף, Bakhi Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef cried. כולי האי
נמי
לאין דומין? Kulei hai nami la'ayin dumin? Is all of these people,
all the righteous people, are worth nothing, like they don't get protected
and it even starts with them? אמר ליה אביי טיבותא הוא לגבייהו.
Amar lei Abayei tivuta hu legabbeihu. No, actually, you know, if it's
going to happen, it's better that it happens to them first. Again,
not exactly fair why they are the ones that suffer, but he's
saying it's actually better that they die first. דכתיב כי מפני הרעה
נאסף הצדיק, dekhtiv ki mipnei hara'a ne'esaf hatzadik, because of the evil,
the righteous person is gathered in and therefore in order so he
doesn't have to see the suffering that is going to come to
the world.
So, you know, very dealing with a lot of, you know, harsh
realities out there and trying to give some type of a religious
explanation or recognition to these things. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the
name of רב, לעולם יכנס אדם בכי טוב ויצא בכי טוב. le'olam
yikanes adam bekhitov veyetze bekhitov. So again about the things about bad
forces out there, a person should always come in if he's traveling,
come into the city while it's still light. וירא אלהים את האור
כי טוב, vayar elohim et ha'or ki tov, so don't be traveling,
you know, make sure you come into the city and you settle
down or whatever while it's still light. Otherwise, you know, there are
bandits and wild animals and so on. ויצא בכי טוב, Veyetze bekhitov,
and when you leave your house, you know, or to go on
a trip or you leave to go to the next city, you
should also make sure that it is light. שנאמר ואתם לא תצאו
איש מפתח ביתו עד בוקר. shene'emar ve'atem lo tetze'u ish mipetach beito
ad boker. Don't go out until the morning. Okay, so wait till
the morning. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan: דבר בעיר כנס רגליך. dever
ba'ir knas raglekha. שנאמר ואתם לא תצאו איש מפתח ביתו עד בוקר.
shene'emar ve'atem lo tetze'u ish mipetach beito ad boker. If there's pestilence
in the city, stay at home. Okay, so, you know, I don't
know, this was מכת בכורות, makat bekhorot, but still this type of
forces that just kill, you know, you can think about a time
of a plague,
Corona, everybody stayed at home. Okay, so, you know, these pandemics, stay
at home because it says don't go out of your house. לא
תצאו איש מפתח ביתו עד בוקר. Lo tetze'u ish mipetach beito ad
boker. ואומר, Ve'omer, and another verse says, לך עמי בא בחדריך וסגור
דלתיך בעדך, lekh ammi bo vakhadarekha usgor daltekha ba'adekha, go my people,
go into your chambers and close your doors. ואומר מחוץ תשכל חרב
ומחדרים אימה, Ve'omer michutz teshakel cherev umichadarim eima, from outside is the
sword and from inside is fear. Okay, so now the sword is
not exactly a pestilence, okay, but still when these type of evil
forces are out there, stay at home. מאי ואומר? Mai ve'omer? Why
do you need extra פסוקים? pesukim? וכי תימא הני מילי בליליא אבל
ביממא לא? Vekhi teima hanei milli beleilya aval biyemama lo? Maybe it's
only, maybe you only have to stay indoors when these bad things
are at night, but not in the daytime. תא שמע לך עמי
בא בחדריך וסגור דלתיך. Ta shema lekh ammi bo vakhadarekha usgor daltekha.
So the next פסוק pasuk is more general, just says stay, you
know, go in and close yourself up. וכי תימא הני מילי היכא
דליכא אימה מגואי? Vekhi teima hanei milli heikha delika eima migavai? Maybe
only close myself up if I'm not also afraid when I'm inside
my house? אבל היכא דאיכא אימה מגואי? Aval heikha de'ika eima migavai?
But if I'm afraid even inside my house? כי נפיק יתיב ביני
אינשי
בצוותא דעלמא טפי מעלי. Ki nafik yatitve beini inshi betzavta de'alma tefei
ma'alei. So then if I'm like trembling and anxious at home, maybe
I should go out and be with people and that will make
me feel better, you know, an interesting question about how people chose
to react at the time of Corona, you know, what it means
to be socially isolated. So the גמרא says, no. תא שמע מחוץ
תשכל חרב ומחדרים אימה, Ta shema michutz teshakel cherev umichadarim eima, from
outside is the sword and from inside is fear and trembling. אף
על גב דמחדרים אימה, Af al gav demichadarim eima, even though you'll
be inside and you'll have fear, מחוץ תשכל חרב, michutz teshakel cherev,
you should know that the sword is making people, you know, bereaved
outside and it's better to remain inside. Okay, fascinating based on things
we've experienced not so long ago. Okay.
רבא בעידן
רתחא הוה סכר כווי. Rava be'iddan ritcha hava sakhar kavei. רבא Rava
at a time of God's anger, which again רש״י Rashi says means
like pestilence or a pandemic, you know, he would close the windows.
דכתיב כי עלה מות בחלונינו, dekhtiv ki ala mavet bekhaloneinu, windows, death
has arisen in our windows. Again, interesting now that we know about
germs and so on. Okay, you know, the idea of social isolation
not to catch it from other people or...
Was there some awareness of, not of the germ theory, but of
the reality here?
But also they're responding to the פסוקים psukim obviously. תנו רבנן: Tanu
rabanan רעב בעיר, ra'av be'ir, if there is
hunger in the city, it's a famine, so then פזר רגליך, pazer
raglecha, leave the city, go out, maybe you'll find another place where
you can find food. Spread out your legs.
שנאמר ויהי רעב בארץ וירד אברם מצרימה. shene'emar vayehi ra'av ba'aretz vayered
Avram Mitzrayma. There was a famine in the land and אברם Avram
went down to Egypt. He didn't stay where he was. Maybe your
luck will be better somewhere else. לגור שם, lagur sham, to live
there. ואומר, ve'omer, another verse says, אם אמרנו נבוא העיר והרעב בעיר
ומתנו. im amarnu navo ha'ir vehara'av ba'ir vamasnu. This is about the
lepers that were מצורעים metzora'im that were outside the city and they
said if we go into the city, well there's a famine in
the city so we will die. So let's rather throw ourselves on
the troops of ארם Aram and we'll risk our lives but maybe
they will take mercy on us and maybe we will live. Okay,
מאי ואומר, mai ve'omer, why do you need another פסוק pasuk after
the פסוק pasuk of אברם? Avram? וכי תימא הני מילי היכא דליכא
ספק נפשות. vechi tima hani mili heicha deleka sofek nefashos. That's only
when if traveling and going out of your city doesn't expose you
to other types of dangers of your life. אבל היכא דאיכא ספק
נפשות, aval heicha de'ika sofek nefashos, but if it exposes you to
other dangers and you're risking your life in other ways, לא maybe
you should just stay where you are. תא שמע לכו ונפלה אל
מחנה ארם אם יחיינו נחיה. ta shma lechu venippela el machaneh Aram
im yechayunu nichyeh. Let's throw ourselves on the troops of ארם, Aram,
if they help us live, we'll live, and if they kill us,
well we're going to die here anyway. Okay, so there you see
even though you're taking risks you should get yourself out and maybe
you will find what to sustain yourself during this period of famine.
Okay, תנו רבנן דבר בעיר אל יהלך אדם באמצע הדרך. Tanu rabanan
dever ba'ir al yehalech adam be'emtza haderech. Now some of this as
we said could be explained in practical terms. This is not going
to seem so practical and it's going to have to do with
a particular metaphysical perspective. If there is pestilence in the city, don't
go in the middle of the road if you're traveling.
מפני שמלאך המות מהלך באמצע הדרכים. mipnei shemalach hamaves mehalech be'emtza haderachim.
Because the מלאך המות, malach hamaves, so you're outside you're supposed to
be inside at a time of pestilence, but if you are outside
because there's all of these forces unleashed and so on, the מלאך
המות malach hamaves has greater, feels very comfortable and he's walking straight
down the middle of the road. So stay out of the middle
of the road. Again, maybe this is also where other people are
so it's good advice in terms of staying away from people. Okay,
דכיון דיהבו ליה רשות decheivan deyahu lei reshus since he's been given
permission to bring his death to the world, so מסגי להדיא, maskei
lehadiya, he walks straight away, he walks in the middle.
שלום בעיר, shalom ba'ir, now if it's a good time in the
city, then איהילך בצידי דרכים ayeilech betzidei drachim then don't go at
the edges, go down the middle of the road. דכיון דלית ליה
רשות decheivan delis lei reshus because since the מלאך המות malach hamaves
does not have permission
to act in public, so מסתפי ומחבי חבויי ומסגי masfei mechabi chibuwei
umaski so he hides and he walks so he walks at the
edges. So then you'll be sort of exposing yourself there to the
evil forces. So when things are good, go with the flow, don't
start going into marginal types of activities is the way we could
read it. Okay, תנו רבנן Rabbanan? come in here. דבר בעיר
אל יכנס אדם יחידי לבית הכנסת. dever ba'ir al yikanes adam yachidi
leveisha knesses. If there's pestilence in the city do not go by
yourself into the home into the שול shul because again the sense
of pestilence, מלאך המות malach hamaves and the מזיקים mazikim and so
on, and when you're with other people you are more protected from
the מזיקים. mazikim. שמלאך המות shemalach hamaves although here it's specifically the
angel of death, מסגי שם כליו maski sham kelav because that's where
the מלאך המות malach hamaves keeps his vessels, right, his scythe and
his other types of things in the בית הכנסת. beis knesses. Why
they're there I don't know, but again בית הכנסת beis knesses was
also not just a שול shul but a gathering place, so maybe
it's speaking about the idea that it's coming out against the whole
population. So the בית הכנסת beis knesses is particularly dangerous, don't go
there alone. והני מילי היכא דלא קרו ביה דרדקי. vehani mili heicha
delo karu bei dardekei. But that's only if there's not a חדר
cheder there, children aren't learning there, ולא מצלו ביה עשרה velo matzu
bei asara there's not a מנין minyan there, but if those things
are happening and there are people present then you'll be protected. Again
even though you're supposed to be in your house during this time.
Okay, תנו
רבנן כלבים בוכים מלאך המות בא לעיר. Tanu rabanan klavim bochim malach
hamaves ba l'ir. If you hear dogs crying, it means that the
מלאך המות malach hamaves is going to come to the city, animals
sensing that something bad is about to happen.
כלבים משחקים klavim mesachakim if the dogs are like yapping and having
a good time, אליהו הנביא בא לעיר, Eliyahu hanavi ba l'ir, that
means that אליהו Eliyahu is coming into the city. והני מילי דלית
בהו נקבה, vehani mili delo is behu nekeiva, but that's only if
there's not a female dog among them, otherwise they might be doing
it because of sexual excitement. Okay, four lines down in the middle
lines. יתיב רב אמי ורב אסי קמיה דרבי יצחק נפחא, Yosiv Rav
Ami veRav Assi kammai deRabbi Yitzchak Nafcha, רב אמי Rav Ami and
רב אסי Rav Assi were sitting in front of רבי יצחק נפחא.
Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha. מר
אמר ליה לימר מר שמעתא. mar amar lei leimar mar shema'ata. One
said, tell us some
הלכה halakha discussion. I want to learn
הלכה. halakha. מר אמר ליה לימר מר אגדתא. mar amar lei leimar
mar aggadta. I want to learn no אגדתא aggadta tell me something
nice, מחשבה machshava related. Okay,
so
פתח למימר אגדתא, patach lemeimar aggadta, so he started to he figured
okay maybe he was more interested in giving a little bit of
a דרשה, drasha, he started to say an אגדתא aggadta ולא שביק
מר velo shavik mar and the other one said no that's not
fair I want to learn הלכה. halakha. פתח למימר שמעתא, patach lemeimar
shema'ata, then he started. Fine, he started teaching הלכה, halacha, ולא שביק
מר, ve-lo shavik mar, the other one said, no, that's not fair,
I want to learn אגדתא. agadata. אמר להם, amar lahem, he said
to them, אמשול לכם משל, emshol lachem mashal, let me give you
a parable. למה הדבר דומה, lema ha-davar domeh, what is this similar
to? לאדם שיש לו שתי נשים, le-adam she-yesh lo shtei nashim, a
person who had two wives, a man had two wives. אחת ילדה
ואחת זקנה, achat yelada ve-achat zekena, a young wife and an old
wife. ילדה מלקטת לו לבנות, yelada melaket lo levanot, the young wife
picks out all of his white hairs from his beard or his
head. זקנה מלקטת לו שחורות, zekena melaket lo shechorot, the old wife
picks out all of his dark hairs, doesn't want him to look
young. נמצאו קרח מכאן ומכאן, nimtzeu kereach mikan u-mikan, he winds up
being bald on this way and this way, bald from his white
hairs and bald from his dark hairs, and then he winds up
being totally bald. Which is a phrase also in modern Hebrew, קרח
מכאן ומכאן. kereach mikan u-mikan. It's sort of like catch-22, either way
you go, you're going to lose,
I'm being pulled in opposite directions and I can't win either way.
Okay, אמר להם, amar lahem, if so, given that this is the
reality, אימא לכו מילתא דשויא לתרוייהו, eima lachum milta de-shavya letarvaihu, let
me tell you something that's good for both of you, a mix
of אגדתא agadata and הלכה, halacha, which by the way was a
classic form in the time of the גמרא and the early גאונים,
Geonim, like the whole שאילתות Sheiltos is a mixture when you give
a דרשה drasha to the people, you start with a הלכה halacha
question and then you give a whole דרשה drasha and in the
course of it you answer the הלכה halacha question. So he's going
to do something similar and it's going to be related to us
which is why we're saying this. So, כי תצא אש ומצאה קוצים,
ki tetze esh u-matza kotzim, if fire goes out and eats the
thistles,
תצא מעצמה. tetze me-atzmah. So goes out, it means like it escaped
you, it wasn't intentional. Fine, תצא מעצמה, tetze me-atzmah, שלם ישלם המבעיר
את הבערה, shalem yeshalem ha-mavir et ha-beirah, the one who actually lit
it should be obligated. So it starts like saying it escaped you
but then it calls the one who's responsible the מבעיר, mavir, the
one who intentionally lit the fire. So this is being understood that
the כי תצא אש ki tetze esh is punishment goes forth from
God, it's like the destruction of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or
suffering, the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and it's not
directly attributable to God in the sense
that we brought it on ourselves, it was our sins. So that's
the תצא מעצמה. tetze me-atzmah. Nevertheless, God is going to treat himself
as the מבעיר mavir and take responsibility for it. אמר הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, עלי לשלם את הבערה שהבערתי. alai leshalem
et ha-beirah she-hivarti. Okay, I'll take responsibility for the fire that I
lit even
though it was your sins. אני הצתי אש בציון, ani hitzati esh
be-Tzion, I'm the one who lit the fire against Zion. שנאמר ויצת
אש בציון, she-ne'emar va-yatzet esh be-Tzion, God lit the fire against Zion,
ותאכל יסודותיה, va-tochal yesodoteha, and it consumed the foundations.
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, and then as a
compensation, ואני עתיד לבנותה באש. ve-ani atid livnotah be-esh. And then as
a compensation, I will build it again, a new בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash with fire. שנאמר ואני אהיה לה חומת אש סביב, she-ne'emar ve-ani
ehyeh lah chomat esh saviv, I will be for it as a
wall of fire round, וכבוד אהיה בתוכה, u-chavod ehyeh be-tochah, and for
glory in its midst. שמעתתא, shmaitata, so that was the אגדתא, agadata,
but you started with a פסוק pasuk which now allows him to
teach הלכה. halacha. פתח וכתב בנזקי ממון וסיים בנזקי גופו. patach ve-chatav
bi-nizkei mamon ve-siyem bi-nizkei gufo. It starts by talking about it's like
your property, like not you did it, the fire went out, so
it's like your ox goes out, but then it calls you the
מבעיר, mavir, the one who lit it. לומר לך אשו משום חציו,
lomar lach esho mishum chitzav, and this supports the position that says
אשו משום חציו, it's an obligation for אדם המזיק adam ha-mazik in
a certain way and not for ממונו המזיק, mamono ha-mazik, a big
סוגיא sugya that we had earlier. Okay, now we're going to have
another discussion about an אגדתא agadata relating to אש and getting into
the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the Rabbis about טמון
באש, tamun be-esh, something hidden in a haystack, are you liable or
not. ויתאוה דוד, Vayyisaveh David, and David desired, this is when he
was with war against the Philistines. ויאמר מי ישקני מים מבור בית
לחם אשר בשער, vayomer mi yashkeni mayim mi-bor Beis Lechem asher ba-sha'ar,
who will give me water from the well of בית לחם Beis
Lechem that's in the gate. ויבקעו שלשת הגבורים במחנה פלשתים, va-yifke'u sheloshet
ha-gibborim be-machaneh Plishtim, and three of the valorous ones went out and
broke through into the camp of the פלשתים, Plishtim, וישאבו מים מבור
בית לחם אשר בשער, va-yish'avu mayim mi-bor Beis Lechem asher ba-sha'ar, and
they drew water for him. So it sounds like maybe they just
needed water, but the גמרא is going to use the classic metaphor
that water is תורה Torah and שער sha'ar is where the זקנים
zekenim sit, so it has to learn about learning תורה Torah from
the זקנים. zekenim. So let's take a look. So it says, מאי
קמבעיא ליה, mai ka miba'ei lei, what was he asking? אמר רבא
אמר רב נחמן, amar Rava amar Rav Nachman, טמון באש קמבעיא ליה.
tamun be-esh ka miba'ei lei. He wanted to know, how do we
פסקן paskin about something
that's hidden in a stack of wheat and a mound of wheat,
and it gets destroyed, do you have to pay for the thing
that's hidden. אי כרבי יהודה אי כרבנן. i-ke-Rabbi Yehuda i-ke-Rabbanan. Is it
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or is it like the רבנן? Rabbanan.
ופשטו ליה מאי דפשטו ליה. u-pashtulei mai de-pashtulei. Now if we knew
the answer, there wouldn't be a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and the רבנן. So they gave an answer, but we don't know
what the answer was. Now why exactly they decided it was
טמון באש, tamun be-esh, we're going to see later that other פסוקים
pesukim around this talks about גדיש, gadish, talks about a pile of
lentils or a pile of wheat, so that sort of provoked the
idea that this was some הלכה halacha question relating to this pile.
And maybe רש''י, Rashi, sort of, could it be theoretical, could it
be that they actually burnt this pile of wheat and they wanted
to know if somebody was liable for the things that were hidden.
רב הונא
אמר, Rav Huna amar, גדישים דשעורים דישראל הוו דהוו מטמרי פלשתים בהו.
gedishim di-se'orim di-Yisrael havu de-havu mitmurei Plishtim behu. No, actually what it
was was that there was a mound of wheat of barley, okay,
because there's one פסוק pasuk that says barley, one פסוק pasuk that
says lentils. Anyway, there was a mound of barley that the Philistines
were hiding in, but the mound—but the barley was owned by a
Jew. וקמיבעיא ליה מהו להציל עצמו בממון חבירו. Vekamiba'aya lei mahu lehatzil
atzmo bemamon chaveiro. Are you allowed to save yourself by destroying your
friend's property? So can we burn down this, this pile
of barley in order to kill our enemies, in order to flush
them out?
Okay, שלחו ליה, shalchu lei, so the answer he got was אסור
להציל עצמו בממון חבירו, assur lehatzil atzmo bemamon chaveiro, you're not allowed
to do it. אבל אתה מלך אתה מלך פורץ לעשות לו דרך,
aval atah melech atah melech poretz la'asot lo derech, but you are
a king and kings have special license, you know, kings can sort
of, you know, just, you know, burst through, break through somebody's field
and make for himself a path in somebody else's property. So you
have special license, you're allowed to do it, ואין מוחין בידו, ve'ein
mochin beyado, nobody would stop. Now this is a very bizarre question,
can you save yourself with your friend's property? I mean, you know,
you're supposed to protect life. The only things you're not allowed to
do to protect life are עבודה זרה, גילוי עריות ושפיכות דמים. avoda
zara, gilui arayot veshpichut damim. So why should you not be—whoever said
you can't go ahead and burn somebody's property? Now you could sort
of say, well, you know, it's a little different when you're
injuring—you know, when you're not just sinning to God, but it's, you
know, you're causing bringing injury to somebody else to save yourself. But
it does say that the thing you can't do is you can't
murder. It doesn't say that you can't do other types of injury.
Can you blind somebody in order to save yourself? Whether because somebody's
holding a gun to your head and says blind them, or because
in a way for you to escape from whatever situation you're in,
this is the only way out. You know, that's an interesting moral
question. That's inflicting permanent injury on somebody, even though obviously it's about
saving a life. Nevertheless, you know, the classic teaching is is that
it's only שפיכות דמים, shpichut damim, only murder. And something like this,
property, and it's not even property that has any unique special emotional
connection, it's just, you know, barley, so why shouldn't you be able
to and then you'll compensate? So תוספות Tosafot actually says, you know,
רש״י Rashi makes it sound like the real question, like the גמרא,
was you allowed. But because of these questions, overwhelmingly the ראשונים Rishonim
say that obviously you're allowed to do it. The question is if
you destroyed it in the process of of פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh,
is there going to be liability or not? And that was the
question. And the answer is yes, there is liability, but as a
king then you do not have to worry about it. You know,
there's also an interesting question about do these laws change at the
time of war? You know, when obviously, you know, are there special
laws at time of war rather than the normal civil laws that
govern? Okay. Let's take a look, we'll do a little bit more.
ורבנן ואיתימא רבה בר מרי אמרו גדישים דשעורים דישראל
הוו—no, Verabbanan ve'eima Rabba bar Mari ameru gidishim desh'orim deYisrael havu no,
it was a different question. There was a pile of barley that
was owned by Jews, or Israelites, וגדישים דעדשים דפלשתים, vegidishim deadashim dePlishtim,
and a pile of what do you call lentils that was owned
by the Philistines. וקמיבעי להו מהו ליטול גדישים של שעורים דישראל ליתן
לפני בהמתו? Vekamiba'ei lehu mahu litol gidishim shel se'orim deYisrael liten lifnei
behemto?
Can we use this barley, take it without permission to feed our—to
feed, you know, our animals, because the animals that they were there
at the time of war, על מנת לשלם גדישים של עדשים דפלשתים?
al menat leshallem gidishim shel adashim dePlishtim? So then we will conquer,
you know, the פלשתים Plishtim and we'll take over, we'll take their
lentils and then we'll pay back
the Israelite who we took this from with lentils, which are worth
a lot more. So in the end he'll benefit from it. But
at the moment, we're stealing. Okay. שלחו ליה, shalchu lei, they sent
to him: חבל ישיב רשע גזילה ישלם. chaval yashiv rasha gezeila yeshallem.
You know, אף על פי שגזילה משלם, af al pi shegezeila meshallem,
even though you're going to pay back for the גזילה, gezeila, רשע
הוא. rasha hu. It's still—you're still wicked. You're not allowed to steal
no matter how much you're going to pay back. אבל אתה, aval
atah, assuming again that it's not a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh issue,
אבל אתה מלך אתה ומלך פורץ לעשות לו דרך. aval atah melech
atah umelech poretz la'asot lo derech. You have license and you don't
have to pay when you want to do things as a king,
ואין מוחין בידו. ve'ein mochin beyado. Okay. And now we'll just read
very—just about the reason that we're focusing on wheat and—or whatever, barley
and lentils and maybe even a גדיש gadish like רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda and the rabbis, because of the פסוקים. pesukim. One פסוק pasuk
in דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim and one פסוק pasuk in שמואל. Shmuel.
בשלמא למאן דאמר לחלופי היינו דכתיב חד קרא ותהי שם חלקת השדה
מלאה עדשים. Bishlama leman de'amar lachalufei hainu dechtiv chad kra vatehi sham
chelkat hasadeh mele'ah adashim. One says that the sort of field was
filled with lentils. וכתיב חד קרא ותהי חלקת השדה מלאה שעורים, Uchtiv
chad kra vatehi chelkat hasadeh mele'ah se'orim, was filled with barley. And
that was exactly the question. אלא למאן דאמר למקלי מאי איכא למימר?
Ela leman de'amar lemakli mai ika lemeimar? But if it was about,
you know, burning it to save yourself and burning where the פלשתים
Plishtim were hiding, hiding, what do the two פסוקים pesukim tell me?
Was it barley or was it the lentils? So אמר לך דהוו
נמי גדישים דעדשים דישראל דהוו מטמרו בהו פלשתים. Amar lach dehavu nami
gidishim deadashim deYisrael dehavu mitamru behu Plishtim. Yeah, both were true. Okay,
they were hiding in one of barley and hiding in one of
עדשים, adashim, and one פסוק pasuk says one and one says the
other, but both of them were true.
Okay, we'll pick up with
this tomorrow.